Register of the Zjednoczenie Polskich Uchodźców w Niemczech records
Hoover Institution Archives
Zjednoczenie Polskich Uchodźców w Niemczech records
1952-2003
2006C40
Hoover Institution Archives
9 manuscript boxes (3.6 linear feet)
Minutes, correspondence, reports, case files, and printed matter relating to relief activities on behalf of Polish refugees in Germany and to Polish émigré activities.
Zjednoczenie Polskich Uchodźców w Niemczech.
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 2006.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Historical Note
Zjednoczenie Polskich Uchodźców w Niemczech (ZPU), or the Union of Polish Refugees in Germany, was established on July 28th, 1951 with the assistance of one of its most prominent members and future president, Kazimierz Odrobny.
ZPU was a legally registered organization with its own statute that outlined its purpose, coverage, and form of organization. When it was created, it became known as the principal Polish organization in Germany. In its initial stages of existence, ZPU was tasked with representing the affairs of all Polish refugees in Germany: those who remained in the country after being released from concentration camps, prisoner-of-war camps, and labor camps. This was especially the case after 1952, when the International Refugee Organization (IRO) ceased to exist and the ZPU took over some of its tasks in representing the Polish community. The ZPU handled many issues of its refugee charges: employment, housing, compensation, legal counsel and assistance with conflicts, organization of education for Polish children, scholarship, cultural events, and more.
ZPU had experienced extensive internal restructuring after the death of Odrobny in 1981. The organization officially ceased to exist in 1993, while under the direction of Andrzej Prusiński.
Scope and Contents of Collection
The collection is composed of materials that reflect the history and activities of the Zjednoczenie Polskich Uchodźców w Niemczech (ZPU), or the Union of Polish Refugees in Germany, and covers the time period from 1952 to 2003. The collection is divided into seven series: administrative file, correspondence file, culture file, Kierownictwo Kolonii Letnich file, Polska Partia Socjalistyczna (PPS) file, Polska Rada Narodowa (PRN) file, and printed matter file. The collection documents the administrative activities and history of the ZPU and its involvement in émigré affairs, as well as the organization’s relationship to various other Polish organizations abroad, through articles, correspondence, bulletins, meeting minutes, reports, communiques, notes, writings, statutes, press releases, and regulations.
International relief.; Poles--Germany (West); Refugees.
- Administrative file, 1957-2003
  Scope and Contents
  Comprised of various documents which reflect the administrative activities of the ZPU. The series is further divided into General Administrative Binder and Związek Organizacji Polskich w Bawarii sections. The majority of documents that appear in this series include: certificates, statistical data, membership declarations, financial records, housing and refugee camps documents, Kongres Wolnej Polski w Europie documents, memos, notifications, notes, information on organization background and history, documents of the Polish American Immigration Relief Committee, press releases, regulations, documents regarding the Polish émigré affairs in Germany, statutes, supplements, meeting minutes, and invitations.
  - Bescheinigung, 1962-1984 (Text : 1: 1)
  - Dane Statystyczne, 1957-1959 (Text : 1: 2)
  - Deklaracje, 1965 (Text : 1: 3)
  - Financial records, 1960-1984 (Text : 1: 4)
  - General Administrative File, 1984 (Text : 1: 5)
  - General Administrative File, A-M, 1959-1961 (Text : 1: 6)
  - General Administrative File, MA-W, 1961-1968 (Text : 1: 7)
  - General Administrative Binder, 1959-1985
    Documents in this grouping include meeting minutes, reports, statutes, correspondence, and communiques. Essentially, documents in this section fit into the larger scope of administrative files. However, the documents were kept together to retain their original order.
    - Porządek dzienny - Protokół, 1968-1975 (Text : 1: 8)
    - Protokoły Zebrań Zarządu Okręgów, 1967-1970 (Text : 1: 9)
    - Protokoły Wolnego Zebrania Ogniska, 1961-1970 (Text : 1: 10)
    - Protokoły Wolnego Zebrania Okręgów, 1959 (Text : 1: 11)
    - Protokoły Zdawczo-Odbiorcze, 1980-1983 (Text : 1: 12)
    - IX - XII, 1984-1985 (Text : 2: 1)
  - Housing and refugee camps, circa 1960 (Text : 2: 2)
  - Komentarze, 1975 (Text : 2: 3)
  - Komisja Rewizyjna, 1983-1984 (Text : 2: 4)
  - Komunikaty, 1984-1985 (Text : 2: 5)
  - Kongres Wolnej Polski w Europie, 1985 (Text : 2: 6)
  - Listy składek członkowskich, 1962-1983 (Text : 2: 7)
  - Memberships, 1959-1984 (Text : 2: 8)
  - Memorandas, 1985 (Text : 2: 9)
  - Mitteilung, 1960-1982 (Text : 2: 10)
  - Notatki i Koncepty, 1960-1984 (Text : 2: 11)
  - Odpisy i dokumenty kierowane do Prezesa Pietraszewskiego, 1984 (Text : 2: 12)
  - Okólnik, 1959-1967 (Text : 2: 13)
  - Organization background, 1960-1984 (Text : 2: 14)
  - Oświadczenia, 1984 (Text : 2: 15)
  - Pełnomocnictwo, 1984 (Text : 2: 16)
  - Pokwitowania, 1959-1963 (Text : 2: 17)
  - Polish American Immigration & Relief Committee Inc., 1960-1961 (Text : 2: 18)
  - Potwierdzenia, 1983 (Text : 3: 1)
  - Poświadczenia, 1978 (Text : 3: 2)
  - Presseerklärung, 1976-1978 (Text : 3: 3)
  - Protokoły, 1959-1984 (Text : 3: 4)
  - Regulaminy, circa 1980 (Text : 3: 5)
  - Sanatorium Gauting, 1959-1965 (Text : 3: 6)
  - Sąd Rejestracyjny, 1984 (Text : 3: 7)
  - Sprawozdania, 1959-1975 (Text : 3: 8)
  - Sprawy emigracji Polskiej w Republice Federalnej Niemiec, 1959-1960 (Text : 3: 9)
  - Satzung, circa 1980 (Text : 3: 10)
  - Supplement, 1981 (Text : 3: 11)
  - Uchwały, 1965-1985 (Text : 3: 12)
  - Upoważnienia, 1965, 1984 (Text : 3: 13)
  - Uwagi, 1984 (Text : 3: 14)
  - Uzasadnienia, 1963 (Text : 3: 15)
  - Vereinbarung, 1964 (Text : 3: 16)
  - Zaproszenia, 1962-1984 (Text : 3: 17)
  - Zawiadomienia, 1965-1984 (Text : 3: 18)
  - Zebrania, 1959-1978 (Text : 3: 19)
  - Zestawienia, 1961, 1965 (Text : 3: 20)
  - Związek Organizacji Polskich w Bawarii, 1988-2003
    This section is composed of administrative documents of the Union of Polish Organizations in Bavaria. Documents represented in this section include: articles, notifications, bulletins, correspondence, information on healthcare for émigrés, statutes, and reports.
    - Administrative records, 1992-1996 (Text : 4: 1)
    - Articles, 1993-2001 (Text : 4: 2)
    - Bescheinigung, 1992 (Text : 4: 3)
    - Biuletyny, 1996-2003 (Text : 4: 4)
    - Bundesministerium Des Innern, 1994-1995 (Text : 4: 5)
    - Correspondence, 1992-1996 (Text : 4: 6)
    - Lekarze Obcokrajowcom, 2001 (Text : 4: 7)
    - Piertraszewski, Eugeniusz, 1988 (Text : 4: 8)
    - Ptaczek, Józef, 2001 (Text : 4: 9)
    - Satzung, 1995 (Text : 4: 10)
    - Sprawozdanie z Obrad Drugiego Zebrania Europejskiej Rady Wspólnot Polonijnych, 1994 (Text : 4: 11)
    - Sznarbachowski, Włodzimierz, 2001 (Text : 4: 12)
    - "Zgoda,", 1994 (Text : 4: 13)
  - Życiorysy, circa 1960s (Text : 4: 14)
- Correspondence, 1952-1986
  Composed of correspondence that pertains to the administrative affairs of the ZPU. Includes letters pertaining to the well-being of Polish émigrés and the manner in which the ZPU handled their various requests or acted on their behalf.
  - Administrative correspondence, B-O, 1959-1961 (Text : 4: 15)
  - Administrative correspondence, P-Z, 1959-1961 (Text : 4: 16)
  - Arłamowski, Jerzy, 1978-1983 (Text : 5: 1)
  - Baca, Stanisław, 1963 (Text : 5: 2)
  - Baca, Stanisław i Niewiarkowska W., 1966-1967 (Text : 5: 3)
  - Barański, Stanisław, 1962 (Text : 5: 4)
  - Barański, Stanisław i Basiewicz, Edmund, 1963-1964 (Text : 5: 5)
  - Barański, Stanisław i Franecki, Józef, 1962 (Text : 5: 6)
  - Barański, Stanisław i Kinas, Józef, 1965-1966 (Text : 5: 7)
  - Barenberg, Norbert, 1981-1982 (Text : 5: 8)
  - Bączek, Władysław, 1961 (Text : 5: 9)
  - Bąk, Józef, 1960-1985 (Text : 5: 10)
  - Bednarczyk, Stanisław, 1962-1966 (Text : 5: 11)
  - Bednarczyk, Stanisław i Maligłowa, Zofia, 1966 (Text : 5: 12)
  - Bednarczyk, Stanisław i Duda, Jan, 1962-1963 (Text : 5: 13)
  - Benkö, Zoltan, 1980 (Text : 5: 14)
  - Białoboki, Witold, undated (Text : 5: 15)
  - Beyer, Erwin, 1965 (Text : 5: 16)
  - Bond, Gerd, 1963 (Text : 5: 17)
  - Bór-Graźewicz, Stefan, 1958-1959 (Text : 5: 18)
  - Broniwój-Orliński, Wincenty, 1980-1986 (Text : 5: 19)
  - Busse, Andrzej, 1984 (Text : 5: 20)
  - Chodakowski, Adam, 1982 (Text : 5: 21)
  - Chróścielewski, Janusz F., 1963 (Text : 5: 22)
  - Chyczewski, Julian, 1964 (Text : 5: 23)
  - Ciesielczyk, Marek, 1981-1982 (Text : 5: 24)
  - Czemplik, Ryszard Reiss, 1981-1985 (Text : 5: 25)
  - Czykieta, Józef, 1959 (Text : 5: 26)
  - Czyż, Roman, 1981 (Text : 5: 27)
  - Dąbkowski, Jarosław i Sawicka, Teresa, 1985 (Text : 5: 28)
  - Dziakoński, Z., 1962 (Text : 5: 29)
  - Elsler, Olga, 1961 (Text : 5: 30)
  - Ettmueller, M. E., 1960-1961 (Text : 5: 31)
  - Fikowski-Schelles, Iwona, 1984 (Text : 5: 32)
  - Förschner, 1965 (Text : 5: 33)
  - Franczak, Wiktor, 1979-1983 (Text : 5: 34)
  - Frendl, Ludwik, 1978-1985 (Text : 5: 35)
  - Fudalewski, Leszek, 1984 (Text : 5: 36)
  - Garztecki, Marek, 1983 (Text : 5: 37)
  - Głowiński, Stefan, 1966 (Text : 5: 38)
  - Halem, Friedrich V., 1984 (Text : 5: 39)
  - Galiński, Jerzy, 1983 (Text : 5: 40)
  - de Gernand, M. J., 1962 (Text : 5: 41)
  - Gołębiewski, Włodzimierz, 1960 (Text : 5: 42)
  - Grabowska, M., undated (Text : 5: 43)
  - Gruszecki, Wojciech, 1984 (Text : 5: 44)
  - Grzesiak, Tadeusz, 1962-1965 (Text : 5: 45)
  - Gutowski, Sczepan, 1960-1964 (Text : 5: 46)
  - Herec, Adam, 1964 (Text : 5: 47)
  - Huszovszky, L., Dr., 1960 (Text : 5: 48)
  - Jach, Kazimierz, 1962-1963 (Text : 5: 49)
  - Jakubowski, Kazimierz, 1963 (Text : 5: 50)
  - Jar-Łańcucki, Janusz, 1959-1961 (Text : 5: 51)
  - Jenkins, H., 1961 (Text : 5: 52)
  - Jędrzejewski, Kazimierz, 1962-1964 (Text : 5: 53)
  - Jooss, Emil, 1959 (Text : 5: 54)
  - Jurak, Barbara, 1981 (Text : 5: 55)
  - Kaczmarczyk, Józef, Dr., 1983 (Text : 5: 56)
  - Kadosa, J. J., Dr., 1963 (Text : 5: 57)
  - Kajka, Paweł, 1964 (Text : 5: 58)
  - Kalinin, Józef, 1965 (Text : 5: 59)
  - Kaminski, Wiktor, 1981 (Text : 5: 60)
  - Keilhohofer, 1965 (Text : 5: 61)
  - Kita, Marek, 1986 (Text : 5: 62)
  - Klink, Dr., 1959 (Text : 5: 63)
  - Konieczny, Janusz, 1984 (Text : 5: 64)
  - Kopera, Lucjan, 1981 (Text : 5: 65)
  - Kostecki, Juzef, 1962 (Text : 5: 66)
  - Kowalski, Jacek, 1978-1986 (Text : 5: 67)
  - Krzyżanowski, Janusz, 1985 (Text : 6: 1)
  - Ktodnicki, Tadeusz, 1981 (Text : 6: 2)
  - Kuk, Karol, 1964 (Text : 6: 3)
  - Kurus, O., 1962, 1965 (Text : 6: 4)
  - Kurus, O. i Błasiak, circa 1960 (Text : 6: 5)
  - Kurus, O. i Jarmusiewicz, A., 1962 (Text : 6: 6)
  - Künstler, 1964 (Text : 6: 7)
  - Lange, Dr., 1960 (Text : 6: 8)
  - Lis, Władysław, 1964-1965 (Text : 6: 9)
  - Litwiniak, Marian, 1962-1985 (Text : 6: 10)
  - Litwiniak, Marian i Dziakoński, Z., 1962 (Text : 6: 11)
  - Litwiniak, Marian i Malkiewicz, Kazimierz, 1965 (Text : 6: 12)
  - Litwiniak, Marian i Pietraszewski Eugeniusz, 1962-1966 (Text : 6: 13)
  - Litwiniak, Marian i Wład, Kazimierz, 1962-1963 (Text : 6: 14)
  - Maj, Jacek, 1981 (Text : 6: 15)
  - Martysiewicz, Dr., 1965 (Text : 6: 16)
  - Matejak, Elżbieta, 1985 (Text : 6: 17)
  - Maurer, Johannes, 1961 (Text : 6: 18)
  - Maziarz, Jan, 1981 (Text : 6: 19)
  - Metzner, Ehrenfried, 1962 (Text : 6: 20)
  - Mikiciuk, Stanisław, 1986 (Text : 6: 21)
  - Morawietz, R., 1962 (Text : 6: 22)
  - Motz, Wacław, 1983 (Text : 6: 23)
  - Newes, K., 1959 (Text : 6: 24)
  - Niedźwiecki, Jan, 1981 (Text : 6: 25)
  - Nowotna, Irena, 1984 (Text : 6: 26)
  - Odrobny, Kazimierz, 1960-1981 (Text : 6: 27)
  - Ogilbianka, Maria, 1984 (Text : 6: 28)
  - Ogrodnik, Danuta, 1981 (Text : 6: 29)
  - Okińczyc, Franciszek, 1959-1965 (Text : 6: 30)
  - Omasta, Josef, 1962, 1965 (Text : 6: 31)
  - Ormicki, L., 1978 (Text : 6: 32)
  - Otulakowski, Stanisław, 1962-1963 (Text : 6: 33)
  - Paberzs, Antoni, 1986 (Text : 6: 34)
  - Pamuła, Jan, Ks., undated (Text : 6: 35)
  - Paterek, W. J., 1984 (Text : 6: 36)
  - Pętlicki, Jerzy, 1984 (Text : 6: 37)
  - Pflüger, Hans, 1981 (Text : 6: 38)
  - Pietraszewski, Eugeniusz, 1952-1986 (Text : 6: 39)
  - Pietraszewski, Eugeniusz, 1955-1985 (Text : 6: 40)
  - Pietraszewski, Eugeniusz i Fusaro, Mieczysława, 1962 (Text : 6: 41)
  - Piętkiewicz, Klemen, Brigitta, 1960 (Text : 6: 42)
  - Piotrowski, J., 1959 (Text : 6: 43)
  - Pisarek, Edward, 1986 (Text : 6: 44)
  - Podgórski, Tadeusz, 1984, 1986 (Text : 6: 45)
  - Poganowska, Katarzyna, 1962-1965 (Text : 6: 46)
  - Polarek, Aleksander, 1981 (Text : 6: 47)
  - Pożoga, Wincenty, 1962-1966 (Text : 6: 48)
  - Pyś, Kazimierz, 1963, 1965 (Text : 6: 49)
  - Reichert, Rudolf, 1965 (Text : 6: 50)
  - Reichert, Rudolf i Tobolik, Jan, 1965-1966 (Text : 6: 51)
  - Ren, Eugen, 1963 (Text : 6: 52)
  - Richter, Gregers, 1961 (Text : 6: 53)
  - Rojemska, L. Koral, 1963 (Text : 6: 54)
  - Rosenbusch, Adam, 1985 (Text : 6: 55)
  - Rudnicki, Ryszard i Sawicki, Teresa, 1983-1985 (Text : 6: 56)
  - Satzger, 1964 (Text : 6: 57)
  - Sawicki, Józef, 1963 (Text : 7: 1)
  - Sawicz, Cz., 1984 (Text : 7: 2)
  - Schirilla, L., 1961 (Text : 7: 3)
  - Sołecki, Piotr, 1965 (Text : 7: 4)
  - Sośniecki, Jan, 1964-1965 (Text : 7: 5)
  - Staniul, Wiktor, 1962 (Text : 7: 6)
  - Szafer, Józef, 1983 (Text : 7: 7)
  - Szarlak, Bogdan, 1980 (Text : 7: 8)
  - Szczeplwioscy, B. S., 1984 (Text : 7: 9)
  - Szewczyk, Ewa, 1965 (Text : 7: 10)
  - Szlachta, Bronisława, 1962 (Text : 7: 11)
  - Szpytko, Tadeusz, 1981 (Text : 7: 12)
  - Szubert, Janusz, 1981 (Text : 7: 13)
  - Szymura, Bronisław, 1979, 1983 (Text : 7: 14)
  - Terrillon, Raymond, 1961 (Text : 7: 15)
  - Tiplt, Alexander, undated (Text : 7: 16)
  - Tobolik, Jan, 1966 (Text : 7: 17)
  - Turowski, Mieczysław, 1984 (Text : 7: 18)
  - Tyc, Roman, 1966 (Text : 7: 19)
  - Unidentified, 1960-1986 (Text : 7: 20)
  - Wawrzyniak, Feliks, 1964-1965 (Text : 7: 21)
  - Wawrzyniak, Feliks i Klippel, Jan, 1962-1964 (Text : 7: 22)
  - Wawrzyniak, Feliks i Pożoga, Wincenty, 1964 (Text : 7: 23)
  - Wiśniewski, Edmund, 1984 (Text : 7: 24)
  - Wład, Kazimierz, 1962-1965 (Text : 7: 25)
  - Wład, Kazimierz i Golonka, Adam, 1963 (Text : 7: 26)
  - Wróbel, Stanisław, 1981 (Text : 7: 27)
  - Wolniak, Jan, 1983 (Text : 7: 28)
  - Wulffert, N., 1959 (Text : 7: 29)
  - Wussow, Barbara, 1959 (Text : 7: 30)
  - Wysocki, Roman, 1962-1965 (Text : 7: 31)
  - Wysocki, Roman i Wład, Kazimierz, 1962 (Text : 7: 32)
  - Zegadło, Henryk, 1981 (Text : 7: 33)
  - Zon, Karol, 1982-1983 (Text : 7: 34)
- Culture, 1960-1986
  Comprised of materials that pertain to the cultural practices of Polish émigrés in Germany. Materials pertain to cemeteries and memorials, museums, holidays and celebrations, as well as documents that refer to the Polish National Independence Day, celebrated on November 11th, and the May 3rd Constitution Day.
  - Cmentarze, 1960-1986 (Text : 7: 35)
  - Muzeum Polskie, 1980 (Text : 7: 36)
  - Obrzędy i Uroczystości, 1961-1966 (Text : 7: 37)
  - Poloniki w Skarbcu Wittelsbachów w Monachium, circa 1960 (Text : 7: 38)
  - “Polnische Damen,”, 1980 (Text : 7: 39)
  - Uroczystości Święta Niepodległości 11-ego listopada, 1966-1980 (Text : 7: 40)
  - Uroczystości 3-cio majowe i Tysiąclecie Chrześcijaństwa, 1962-1982 (Text : 7: 41)
- Kierownictwo Kolonii Letnich, 1959-1965
  Documents in this section refer to education, children, and summer camps that were sponsored by the ZPU. Materials included are: applications, health insurance forms, financial records, programs, and communiques.
  - Children and Education, 1959-1965 (Text : 7: 42)
  - Correspondence, 1962 (Text : 7: 43)
  - Brown Binder, 1962
    The Kierownictwo Kolonii Letnich series includes documents which came from a brown binder. The binder has been deconstructed, and the documents have been retained in their original order as they appeared in the binder. Documents included in this section pertain to the administrative planning stages of the summer camps for children.
    - Przygotowanie, 1962 (Text : 7: 44)
    - Ministerstwo, 1962 (Text : 7: 45)
    - Caritas, 1962 (Text : 7: 46)
    - Różne Pisma Niemieckie, 1962 (Text : 7: 47)
    - Zarząd Główny, 1962 (Text : 7: 48)
    - Różne Organizacje, 1962 (Text : 7: 49)
    - Sprawy Personalne, 1962 (Text : 7: 50)
    - Kolonie, 1962 (Text : 7: 51)
  - Red Binder, 1962
    The Kierownictwo Kolonii Letnich series includes documents which came from a red binder. The binder has been deconstructed, and the documents have been retained in their original order as they appeared in the binder. Documents included in this section pertain to the administrative planning stages of the summer camps for children.
    - Amberg, 1962 (Text : 8: 1)
    - Augsburg, 1962 (Text : 8: 2)
    - Correspondence, 1962 (Text : 8: 3)
    - Dillingen, 1962 (Text : 8: 4)
    - Ingolstadt, 1962 (Text : 8: 5)
    - Landshut, 1962 (Text : 8: 6)
    - Ludwigsfeld, 1962 (Text : 8: 7)
    - München-m, 1962 (Text : 8: 8)
    - Nürnberg, 1962 (Text : 8: 9)
    - Rosenheim, 1962 (Text : 8: 10)
    - Herzongenaurach, 1962 (Text : 8: 11)
    - Neu-Ulm, 1962 (Text : 8: 12)
    - Ppuł. Majewski, 1962 (Text : 8: 13)
    - Zirndorf/Nürnberg, 1962 (Text : 8: 14)
    - Deggendorf, 1962 (Text : 8: 15)
  - Financial, 1962 (Text : 8: 16)
  - General Local Health Insurance, 1962 (Text : 8: 17)
  - Komunikaty, 1962 (Text : 8: 18)
  - Programy, 1962 (Text : 8: 19)
  - Recovery Care, 1962 (Text : 8: 20)
  - Wykaz dzieci zgłoszonych na wyjazd i naukę w Anglii z terenu IV Okręgu ZPU, 1962 (Text : 8: 21)
- Polska Partia Socjalistyczna, 1964-1986
  Composed of documents pertaining to the relationship between ZPU and Polska Partia Socjalistyczna. Documents included in this series are: appeals, articles, asylum requests, bulletins, correspondence, pamphlets, press releases, and writings.
  - Appell, 1981 (Text : 8: 22)
  - Articles, 1964-1984 (Text : 8: 23)
  - Asylrecht, circa 1980 (Text : 8: 24)
  - Bulletines, 1980-1983 (Text : 8: 25)
  - Correspondence, 1979-1986 (Text : 8: 26)
  - Informacja, 1982 (Text : 8: 27)
  - Nazwiska z “Tablicy Katyńskiej,”, undated (Text : 8: 28)
  - Okólnik, 1980-1983 (Text : 8: 29)
  - Pamphlets, circa 1986 (Text : 8: 30)
  - Prace nad Założeniem do Platformy Programowej P.P.S., 1984 (Text : 8: 31)
  - Presseerklärung, 1981-1983 (Text : 8: 32)
  - Solidarność, 1982 (Text : 8: 33)
  - Stosunki Polsko-Niemieckie, 1979 (Text : 8: 34)
  - Writings, 1979-1984 (Text : 8: 35)
  - Zaproszenia, 1984 (Text : 8: 36)
  - Zawiadomienia, 1982 (Text : 8: 37)
  - Zjazd P.P.S na Obczyźnie, 1981 (Text : 8: 38)
- Polska Rada Nardowa, 1978-1986
  Comprised of documents relating to the relationship between ZPU and Polska Rada Narodowa. Documents included in the series are: appeals, bulletins, correspondence, membership information, communiques, notes, meeting minutes, and writings.
  - Apele, 1981 (Text : 9: 1)
  - Biuletyny, 1979 (Text : 9: 2)
  - Correspondence, 1979-1984 (Text : 9: 3)
  - Członkowstwo, circa 1980 (Text : 9: 4)
  - Komunikaty, 1979-1980 (Text : 9: 5)
  - List Wierzytelny, 1986 (Text : 9: 6)
  - Notatki, circa 1980 (Text : 9: 7)
  - Orędzia, 1982 (Text : 9: 8)
  - Oświadczenia, 1978-1980 (Text : 9: 9)
  - Posiedzenia, 1978-1984 (Text : 9: 10)
  - Powstanie Polskiej Rady Narodowej w Republice Niemiec, 1978-1979 (Text : 9: 11)
  - Skarb Narodowy w Rzeczypospolitej Polskiej, 1979-1980 (Text : 9: 12)
  - Statuty i Przepisy, circa 1980 (Text : 9: 13)
  - Writings, 1979 (Text : 9: 14)
  - Zaproszenia, 1982-1983 (Text : 9: 15)
  - Zebrania, 1981-1983 (Text : 9: 16)
- Printed Matter, 1970-1982
  Documents in this section represent printed matter that was collected or produced by ZPU. Materials included are: articles, bulletins, clippings, poems, writings, and a couple publications of the bulletin Rodak.
  - Articles, 1978-1981 (Text : 9: 17)
  - Biuletyny, 1977-1982 (Text : 9: 18)
  - Clippings, circa 1980 (Text : 9: 19)
  - Poems, circa 1980 (Text : 9: 20)
  - Rodak, circa 1980 (Text : 9: 21)
  - Writings, 1970-1982 (Text : 9: 22-23)